Guide to the American Nature Study records, 1908-1997.
American Nature Study records, 1908-1997.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
American Nature Study records, 1908-1997.
2195
American Nature Study Society.
5.2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, newsletters, membership lists, marked ballots, minutes, reports, memoranda, offprints, pamphlets, programs, accounts, constitutions and printed items.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence of society secretary-treasurers Nellie Matlock and Richard L. Weaver and the Conservation Committee; correspondence with the U.S. Department of the Interior, senators and congressmen, and other groups concerning legislation on national parks, grazing lands, irrigation and reclamation projects, and other aspects of forest, soil, and wildlife conservation and national land use policy; letters dealing with annual meetings and with the printing and distribution of Canadian Nature, the society's publication.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence of society secretary-treasurers Nellie Matlock (1937-1940) and Richard L. Weaver (1943-1949) and the Conservation Committee (1947-1949); correspondence (1947-1948) with the U.S. Department of the Interior, senators and congressmen, Izaak Walton League, Ecologists Union, National Council of State Garden Clubs, and other groups concerning legislation on national parks, grazing lands, irrigation and reclamation projects, and other aspects of forest, soil, and wildlife conservation and national land use policy; letters dealing with annual meetings and with the printing and distribution of Canadian Nature, the official publication of the society. Also, newsletters, membership lists, marked ballots, minutes, reports, memoranda, offprints, pamphlets, programs, accounts, constitutions and other printed items. Also, correspondence, announcements, and membership and mailing lists of the American Association for the Advancement of Science and the Natural Resources Council of America and resolutions and press releases of the National Parks Association.
Also, correspondence of Ephraim Laurence Palmer, professor of rural education at Cornell University, officer and active member of the society, with Bertha Chapman Cady, William L. Finley, George R. Green, Edith Patch, Ellen Eddy Shaw, Otis W. Caldwell, C. Girard Davidson, George Free, Ruth Miriam Gillmore, Samuel H. Ordway, Jr., L.B. Sharp, Dwight E. Solberger, Edwin Way Teale, William Gould Vinal, Richard W. Westwood, and Farida Wiley.
Files and miscellany from Howard Weaver's term as president of the Nature Study Society in 1966 and later.
SUBJECTS
Names:
American Nature Study Society.; Cady, Bertha Chapman.; Caldwell, Otis W.; Davidson, C. Girard.; Finley, William L.; Free, George.; Gillmore, Ruth Miriam.; Green, George R.; Matlock, Nellie F.; Ordway, Samuel H.,; Palmer, Ephraim Laurence, 1888-1970.; Patch, Edith.; Sharp, L. B.; Shaw, Ellen Eddy.; Sollberger, Dwight E.; Teale, Edwin Way, 1899-; Vinal, William Gould.; Weaver, Howard.; Weaver, Richard L.; Westwood, Richard W.; Wiley, Farida A. (Farida Anna); American Association for the Advancement of Science.; American Nature Study Society.; American Nature Study Society.Conservation Committee.; Ecologists Union (U.S.); Izaak Walton League of America.; National Council of State Garden Clubs.; National Parks Association (U.S.); Natural Resources Council of America.; United States.Department of the Interior.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources.; Forest conservation.; Land use--Law and legislation.; Nature study.; Science--Study and teaching.; Soil conservation.; Wildlife conservation.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Nellie F. Matlock files
  - Correspondence, 1924-1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-July 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Sept.-Dec. 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-Mar. 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Apr.-Sept. 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Oct. 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Nov. 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Dec. 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-Feb. 1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Mar.-June 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, July-Oct. 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, Nov. 1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, Dec. 1940-May 1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- R.L. Weaver files
  - Correspondence with Ralph Dexter and misc. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence with Dr. Otis Caldwell (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence with George Free (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence with Charles E. Mohr (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence with E.L. Palmer (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence with L.B. Sharp (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence with Ellen Eddy Shaw (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence of Ellen Eddy Shaw - E.L. Palmer (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence with Dr. Dwight E. Sollberger (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence with Dr. Dwight E. Sollberger (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence with Edwin Way Teale (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence with William Gould Vinal (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence with R.W. Westwood (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence with Farida Wiley (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence "N-P" (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence "R" (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence "S" (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence "T" (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence "W" (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence "U-Z" (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence Subscriptions (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-Apr. 1948 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, May-Dec. 1948 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-Feb. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, Mar.-Dec. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Photographs, envelope (Box 1, Folder 50)
- E.L. Palmer files
  - Commander E. Breck (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bertha Chapman Cady (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - L. Lenore Conover (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cornell University - misc. correspondence, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Victor L. Crowell (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - C.E. Douglas (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Elizabeth Downhour (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - William L. Finley (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - George R. Green (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Theodosia Hadley (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Jennie Hall, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Jennie Hall, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Russell F. Lund (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Harold I. O'Bryne, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Edith Patch (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - P. Victor Peterson (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - H. Radcliff (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1950 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1959 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Misc. correspondence (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Misc., 1925-1935, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
- A.N.S.S. general files
  - AAAS - correspondence and announcements, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - AAAS - correspondence and announcements, 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Form letters to members, officers, and directors (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Conservation Committee (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Natural Resources Council of America (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Natural Parks Association Release (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Congressional letters: Land Grab Fight, etc. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Canadian Nature - A.R. Whitemore-Mary Light, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Canadian Nature - A.R. Whitemore-Mary Light, 1945-1948 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - New York chapter (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Bangor Bird Conservation Club (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Pittsburgh Club (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Watchung Nature Club: New Jersey section (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - St. Louis Nature Club (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Webster Groves Nature Club (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Eastern Nazarene College Club (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Mailing list and other misc., 1928-1936 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Membership lists, 1941-1944 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Membership lists, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Membership lists, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Mailing lists, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Financial accounts (notebook) (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Minutes (notebook), 1951-1956 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Report of Secretary (notebook) (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Treasurer's Report (notebook) (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Special Reports (notebook) (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Programs: Annual Meetings (notebook) (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Elections - ballots (notebook) (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Announcements, letters, and ballots (notebook) (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Ballots, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ballots, letters, statements, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ballots, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Nominations, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Ballots, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Reports and minutes, 1926-1932 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Reports and minutes, 1926-1932, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Boston Meeting, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Boston Meeting, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Boston Meeting, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - St. Louis Meeting - AAAS-ANSS, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chicago papers, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Business Meeting - Chicago, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Chicago Meeting - correspondence, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Chicago Meeting - correspondence, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Washington - Joint meeting - ANSS, NABT, NSTA, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Washington, DC, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Washington, DC (and general), 1948 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - New York, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Speeches and writings (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Original drawings (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Certificate of Incorporation (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - President - signatures (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Constitutions, 1931-1939, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Printed matter and reprints (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Pamphlets (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Programs, 1926-1938, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Newsletter msss. ANSS (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Newsletter file (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Newsletter, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Newsletter, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Newsletter, Spring 1945 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Newsletter, Summer 1945 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Newsletter, Fall 1945 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Newsletter, Fall-Winter 1945 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Newsletter, Spring 1946 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Newsletter, Winter 1946 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - ANSS Newsletters (bound), 1937-1946 (Box 4)
  - ANSS Newsletters (loose leaf), 1947-1961 (Box 4)
  - ANSS Minutes and Records (loose leaf), 1925-1941 (Box 4)
  - Gavel, scroll made from Liberty Hyde Bailey's walking stick and remaining top of stick; pen (Box 5)
  - Nature-Study Review issues, Jan. 1905-Dec. 1919 (Box 6)
  - The Naturalists Diary for Outdoor Use - by William Gould Vinal, 1930 (Box 8)
  - Common Water Insects: A Field Study Guide - by Ann H. Morgan (Box 8)
- A.N.S.S. files, ca. 1960-ca. 1980
  - Historical (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Promotional (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Consolidated Edison proposal (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Urban Workshops (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous activities (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Trinidad & Tobago trip (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Ballots and officers (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Membership correspondence (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Membership directories (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Meeting agenda and minutes (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Treasurer's reports (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Legal documents (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Richard J. Baldauf file (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Kathleen Blanchard file (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - John A. Gustafson file (1) (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - John A. Gustafson file (2) (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Publications Committee file, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Publications Committee file, 1965-1968 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Publications Committee file, 1968-1970 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Publications Committee file, 1975-1980 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Nature Study special issue on William Gould Vinal (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Nature Study special issue on Robert Frost (his centennial, 1974) (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Nature Study issue "Youth and Environment" (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - "News & Notes" materials (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Newsletters, 1955-1963 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - "City Critters" file (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - J.W. Brainerd offprints (Box ?)
  - "Liberty Hyde Bailey Award" (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "Eva L. Gordon Award" (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Program and speakers for Annual Meeting (Philadelphia), 1962 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Photographs (1) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Photographs (2) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - NAAS Leaflets project (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Girl Scout Bird Project booklet and Naturalists Diary, 1922, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Nature Study - A Sampler of Tips, Vol. 48, No. 1-4, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Howard Weaver files, 1957-1992 (Box 8, Folder 9)